if you've been considering building your
very own custom Dream Home in Central
Texas this video is for you hi I'm
Andrea dudic associate broker and
realtor with f real estate here with my
friend and Builder Glenn Morrison with
wellmer homes and today we'll be
discussing the home building process and
the different opportunities that are
available to you if you're looking to
build a custom home so again I'm here
with Glenn we met about a year ago on a
different home and we've continued to
work together ever since and is just a
fantastic Builder and someone I really
feel proud to refer my clients to um
we're currently standing in actually the
second home that we've built together
the third that I've referred him to and
it's a really beautiful home we'll
actually I'll actually do another video
on this one coming soon so you can get a
full tour so stay tuned for that but
Glenn why don't you tell everyone I
guess a little bit about yourself as a
builder yeah Glenn Morrison I'm co-owner
of wellmore homes been in the business
for several years now having retired
from mpal government back in 2016 uh we
take great pride in what we do
especially with our custom clients it's
a real opportunity to get exactly what
you want and we want to take the
pressure off and just make the the
process so much easier that you can
relax and enjoy the build and he does a
great job at that so there are quite a
few different builders in the areas you
have some big production builders that
really build in bulk I guess they
purchase Lots in a particular Community
they have homes available sometimes you
can do a semic custom with them and I'd
be happy to speak with you about that
but um then you have some of your
smaller custom Builders what would you
call yourself we're a custom build
although we do specs also but for the
most part custom but but he's not a big
production Builder and so actually one
of the things that I really love about
that is that I know that he's able to
give that attention to detail because
he's only going to build what you say 10
to 12 a year doesn't houses a year yes
and so he's out I know that he's going
to be out every single day he himself as
the builder at the house checking on
things and giving me updates so I
actually really love that process
actually in fact I'll never forget
pulling up to our last one and we were
in a water drought and you were standing
outside water in the grass and I'm just
like that's lovely but anyway so you
have a lot of options when building a
home and it's really important to speak
with a reputable realtor maybe even
interview mple Builders so that you can
find a good match for you and find out
what scenario works best for you it's
not so much is just I want to build a
custom house Builder build it there you
have a lot of different financing
options um there's just a lot of
different costs associated with it and
everything just needs to be really
really clear well on this particular
home Glenn already owned the lot and so
my client we met with three different
Builders I brought her three different
Builders because I want wanted her to
see the different options and the types
of homes that they built but more
importantly the relationship that she
was getting with the builder because
they can all structure their fees a
little bit a little less I mean they're
all going to come in varying prices but
at the end of the day you really want to
be proud of the home that you're in see
the work of the Builder and and have
that strong relationship she met with
three Builders she ended up going with
Glenn not surprised I had a feeling that
they would click really well and she is
ecstatic about this home so you can see
behind me we've already start I it's
already done it is beautiful you have
three different ways that you can go
about it number one you can do a true
custom home where you as the buyer you
pick your lot you get a land loan you
purchase the land then you go and get a
construction loan typically 20% down on
that that first draw on the loan pays
off the land and then of course you'll
be already working with the builder at
that time and the Builder will work with
the bank and draws will be authorized to
build on the house you start paying
interest on the draws that have come out
to build so you're making payments then
right so you can see at that point
you've come out of pocket yes quite a
bit for your dream which you know if you
can do that wonderful get your dream lot
and get your true custom home where
you're picking your floor plan and all
of the selections and you have that
budget but your realtor and Builder are
going going to help you stay on budget
and find what that is at the end of that
build process for a true custom you
would do a permanent loan you know your
30-year fixed rate mortgage whether
that's conventional FHA VA now if you do
a semic custom home which is what these
buyers did it's actually a really
awesome opportunity because they and you
don't necessarily have to carry that
interm financing you don't have to take
out that loan you can meet with a
builder pick one of the lots that they
already have purchased and in their name
and do a semic custom pick one of the
different floor plans that they have
they may let you make some tweaks to it
yes we did hear we did hear you'll want
to watch that video cuz the doggy
station doggy shower was custom and
she's so happy about it they'll let you
make the selections that are within
budget and then all you're doing is
signing that contract making your
selections Within the Builder's
wheelhouse and then at the end you're
just doing a regular loan so that is a
really great option as a semic custom
because really to me there's not a huge
difference unless you have some crazy
wild floor plan and maybe there's a
particular lot that you want to buy in a
particular area but semic custom is a
really great route to go it is and no
money out of pocket other than I guess
your earnest money and any upgrades that
you want to do but again we could go go
over all of that the third option is
going to be a spec home so that is going
to be a home that a builder has already
started it's within their inventory
they've they've made the selection on
the floor plan they made the interior
selections and colors and depending
where you catch the Builder you they may
you know depending on on their
preference allow you to make certain
changes maybe you want white paint
instead of gray maybe you want an
upgrade but we can we can always discuss
the different Builders and and who will
do that absolutely but the spec homes
are generally the Builder has already
made the selections based off of what's
affordable and what's in budget at that
time and as time goes on those costs go
up so picking a speck home you're
generally going to get a better deal
than if you are to start from the ground
up you have the national builders that
have Speck homes everywhere and they're
wonderful you have a smaller outfit kind
of like well more homes our specs might
be a little bit different we do take
great pride in those also we want to
make sure that they're quality because
we know we have a a warranty period the
owner is going to have a 203e loan and
hopefully it's their forever home so you
want to make sure it's it's nice from
from the start but it is a great way to
go for the most part the selections will
fit the need there's somebody for every
house is what we've found and he brings
up a great point you know some of the
national Builders some of those
production Builders they each have
different costs and and fall into
different ranges and they're different
for each person you know sometimes you
get firsttime home buyers where their
priority is a lower budget but a lot
more square footage well some of those
production Builders can get that bigger
square footage but they remove little
upgrades that you might get with other
builders things that are we call them
standard features things that are
standard for Glenn you know might be
different than things that are standard
for Omega or another builder in the area
but again that's what your realtor is
here for you know my job is to stay
familiar with the area what homes are
available what Builders are available
their reputation um what working with
them is like and to help make all of
that really smooth and identifying what
your goals are in the build process so I
think that that was a good thing that
you brought up because everything's a
little bit different one of the things
that I really love about Glenn that I
think has kept me coming back in
addition to his like winning and
hilarious
personality is just Integrity I mean I I
know that if because the reality in real
estate is stuff always comes up there
are so many parties involved there are
so many trades involved good news is
Glenn is always here to lay eyes on it
and catch those things early on and if
something comes up I know it's going to
get resolved and I know that there's
going to be communication about it and
um another thing about that is he'll do
things that he's generous I don't want
to make you give away the farm and say
well said but I'll come in and there'll
be there'll be what what uplight sofit
yes on the front of the home and he'll
say surprise it's a custom home I think
they deserves it ex just threw it in so
stuff like that's really cool or I know
I said they're going to have a a shower
curtain but we went ahead and installed
a shower drawer I mean just little nice
things that I appreciate as a realtor
and I know my clients really do too
because they know it goes above and
beyond and I don't know it's very
respectable and appreciated thank you so
is there anything Glenn that you would
add in terms of I guess between we have
our Custom semic Custom and speculative
is there anything that you would add on
to those yeah so I'm just going to
piggyback what you said I think in a
custom build it's about a relationship
from the very start so being honest and
open from the start and I agree I think
a person or a family that's going to
build a custom I think they ought to
interview some people multiple Builders
because there is is that that sweet spot
that you'll find that you trust a person
and you know it's going to be a a good
process so we encourage that uh my
partner and I we build a dozen or so a
year and every one of them that we have
great respect for whether it's a spec a
customer what but to know that the
trades that they have that follow them
throughout the build like we haven't
lost or got rid of a trade in years they
do great work from Building Inspections
they're already dead on when they do
their work and then they don't mind when
the walls are open that if we have to
make a change we can do it right then
and there and they don't make a big deal
of it because they know it is a custom
home and this is an opportunity for that
person to get exactly what they want so
again just take your time and find that
right fit whether it's WM more homes or
someone else and because uh it it is
that relationship yep I love that that's
so true okay so again of course I'm
going to express why I'd love to work
with you but I really do think it's
important in working with a realtor in
this process just like you're
interviewing a builder interview your
Realtors because not everyone's going to
be your cup of tea and you're going to
mesh well with some others but I want to
be here to advocate for you I want to be
able to say I think that this option I I
want you to see this other option I want
you to to see what other homes are out
there what other builders are out there
what other incentives we can get you at
the end of the day my job is to
represent you and then the the Builder
of course is's going to look out for you
but you also want an advocate to kind of
guide the entire process so thanks so
much Glenn for taking the time to speak
to me and speak to everyone about just
you as a builder and your experiences if
you are interested in building your very
own custom dream home we'd love to speak
with you book a call below let's discuss
what you're looking for maybe a custom
home isn't what you're looking for at
the moment maybe you're really looking
for a move in ready home make sure you
watch this next video of my property
tour of a beautiful luxury KS built home
in belon Texas until next time I'm
Andrea dudic your central Texas real
estate expert wait